<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon appointed for Saint Pauls Crosse, but preached in Saint Pauls Church, on the day of His Maiesties happy inavgvration. March 27. 1642. By Richard Gardyner, D.D. and Canon of Christ-Church, Oxon.</title>
            <author>Gardiner, Richard, 1591-1670.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1642</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 47 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 21 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A85798</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing G231</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E141_29</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R16286</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99860006</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99860006</idno>
            <idno type="VID">112111</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A85798)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 112111)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 25:E141[29])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon appointed for Saint Pauls Crosse, but preached in Saint Pauls Church, on the day of His Maiesties happy inavgvration. March 27. 1642. By Richard Gardyner, D.D. and Canon of Christ-Church, Oxon.</title>
                  <author>Gardiner, Richard, 1591-1670.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 35, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for R. Royston, at the signe of the angell in Ivy-Lane,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1642.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "the sermon I heard preached".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Charles --  I, --  King of England, 1600-1649 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  Timothy, 1st, I, 2 --  Sermons --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Puritans --  England --  Sermons --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Dissenters, Religious --  England --  Sermons --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>Geremy Carnes</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>Geremy Carnes</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:112111:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A SERMON Appointed For Saint Pauls Croſſe, But Preached In Saint Pauls Church, ON THE DAY OF HIS MAIESTIES HAPPY INAVGVRATION.</p>
            <p>MARCH 27. 1642.</p>
            <p>By <hi>RICHARD GARDYNER, D. D.</hi> and Canon of Chriſt-Church, <hi>Oxon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>R. Royſton,</hi> at the ſigne of the Angell in Ivy-Lane. 1642.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:112111:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:112111:2"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT HONOVRABLE, EDWARD, EARLE OF DORSET. The grand encourager of my ſtudies.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>My Lord,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Auditors of this Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon have paſſed their verdict that the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plection thereof is ſtrong enough to come abroad, and to endure the publique Aire.
<pb facs="tcp:112111:3"/>Their diffuſive charity procured the meanes of communicating it to more eares, and eyes then their owne: But I am reſolved it ſhall flye no further then your Lordſhip ſhall pleaſe to adde wings to it. The conſcience of gratitude promptes me to acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge that I have ripened, and growne to maturity by the warme beames of your noble favour, and ſo encourageth me to crave the ſame indulgent influ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence upon this later iſſue of my braine. The Dialect diſcovers that it is not of a different extraction from my for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Labours. For freely, and ſincere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly it ſpeaks out the Dictates of a heart ſound, and true to the King, and Country. This ſupports me to walke as it were upon the ridge of a houſe, with ſuch a ſteady pace, that ſecurely I overlooke all dangers, which might
<pb facs="tcp:112111:3"/>enſue by lapſing on the dexter, or ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter ſide. The ſmart of ſome like a Sea-mark hath warned me to decline thoſe Rockes, and Shelves, whereon incautelouſly they have ſplit. And yet leſt the medicine here preſcribed ſhould turne to a wound, I have atti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red Truth with an in offenſive dreſſe, and tempered it with modera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; well knowing that gentle lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage hath oft beene prevalent, where the boyſtrous ſword could not. To expunge miſconſtructions, and to cleare all ſcruples, I have anatomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed, and laid open my whole inward man touching ſome Doctrinals, and Circumſtantials now much agitated, and wherein I might be miſtaken; hoping thereby to ſtand upright in the Judgement of Knowing Men, whom alone I care to ſatisfie.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:112111:4"/>
            <p>
               <hi>My Lord,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The drift of the Diſcourſe is to ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment together affectionate obedience in the People, and cheerefull prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction in the Soveraigne. The one be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the higheſt felicity of the King, and the other the greateſt bleſsing of the Subject. The compleating of which happineſſe, is Your Honors day<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly practiſe; and ſhall ſtill be the ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, and prayer of</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Lordſhips obliged in all Obſervance, RICHARD GARDYNER.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:112111:4"/>
            <head>A SERMON VPON THE DAY OF THE KING'S INAVGVRATION.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>1 TIM. 2.1, 2.</bibl>
                  <p>J exhort therefore that firſt of all ſupplications, prayers, interceſsions, and giving of thankes be made for all men:</p>
                  <p>For Kings and for all that are in Authority, that we may leade a quiet and peaceable life, in all godlineſſe, and honeſty.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>HEN vice growes ſo impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent that it out-braves <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority,</hi> and dares adventure upon the danger of it, it were cowardize in a <hi>Governour</hi> to be blank'd. This made Saint <hi>Paul,</hi> whoſe
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:112111:5"/>uſuall method was to cure by ſoft, and eaſie wayes, to ſtand upon his <hi>Apostle ſhip,</hi> and, as 'tis regiſtred in the cloſe of the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedent Chapter, to cenſure <hi>Hymeneus</hi> and <hi>Alexander,</hi> becauſe for ſome by reſpects, they quitted their Station, and apoſtated from their faith, and religion. Now that this, and the like awing Acts might be more ſucceſſefull, he exhorts us to mixe our ſoules in an unanimous devotion, that ſo a bleſſing may deſcend upon that <hi>Government,</hi> which concernes the good of all, whether of <hi>delinquents,</hi> that they may be <hi>reform'd,</hi> or not delinquents, that they may be <hi>forewarned,</hi> or the <hi>Common di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rective Head</hi> of them both, that the influ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of his <hi>Power</hi> may be more effectuall in the orderly guiding of the <hi>body politique.</hi> So that the Text is an <hi>Exhortation,</hi> Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a duty with its ſeverall branches, <hi>J exhort therefore, that firſt of all Supplications, Prayers, Interceſsions, and Thankeſgivings be made;</hi> The <hi>object</hi> is firſt laid downe gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally, for <hi>all men;</hi> and then particularly, for the moſt <hi>Eminent</hi> of all men, for <hi>Kings;</hi> and ſo by rule of ſubordination, <hi>for all that
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:112111:5"/>be in Authority;</hi> The <hi>end,</hi> to lead <hi>a quiet, and peaceable life;</hi> the <hi>qualification,</hi> in <hi>all godlineſſe, and honeſty.</hi> I muſt begin, as I am exhorted, firſt of all with <hi>Prayers, Supplications, Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſsions,</hi> and <hi>Thankſgivings.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Eye</hi> of Nature could diſcerne,
<note place="margin">Ariſtes.</note> That Man by nature, is a Suppliant to his Maker; and the <hi>Light</hi> of the World did foreſee that this tribute of Prayer would be tender'd e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very where, ſo that not doubting of the <hi>matter,</hi> he inſtructs in the <hi>forme.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Matth. 6.</note> When you <hi>Pray, Pray thus.</hi> The old people of <hi>Rome</hi> held it in ſuch a religious eſteeme, that they did inſtitute a publique Officer, by the name of <hi>Conditor Precum,</hi> the <hi>Compiler</hi> of Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plications, whoſe taske was to make par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular <hi>Collects</hi> upon gratulations for evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent benefits. And not onely <hi>Rome,</hi> but the Inhabitants of the round world us'd prayer as an Introduction for the happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of all their deſignes. Still they went to worke <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> by invocating their <hi>Tutelar God.</hi> Our Church in Celebrating this hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py <hi>Jnauguration</hi> of our <hi>King.</hi> begins firſt of all with Prayers, Supplications, Interceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:112111:6"/>and Thankeſgiving, as with the prime, and principall part of Gods Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip. For which reaſon the Houſe of <hi>God</hi> is denominated the houſe of Prayer, it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the exerciſe of the Church <hi>Militant</hi> here, and of the <hi>Triumphant</hi> above. Certainely that religious <hi>Queene Elizabeth</hi> us'd earneſtly by prayer to wraſtle with the <hi>Almighty,</hi> as <hi>Jacob</hi> did, for a bleſſing, and obtained it ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly: For out of a Comfortable feeling ſhee frequently us'd to ſay, as Maſter <hi>Cambden</hi> relates, ſhe had rather by prayer talke de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voutly with God, than heare others ſpeak eloquently of God. I ſay no more of the two excellent duties of Praying, and Preaching but onely this, Let not the one juſtle out the other, but let them goe hand in hand together, that <hi>God</hi> may be thereby Glorified, and the <hi>Church</hi> Edified.</p>
            <p>To keepe my ſelfe to the words of my Text, I muſt acquaint you that by <hi>Supplica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions</hi> we declare our humility; by <hi>Prayer</hi> we proclaime a Deity; by <hi>Interceſsion</hi> we make way for Charity; by <hi>Thankeſgiving</hi> wee cheere up, and keepe warme the very life of
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:112111:6"/>Piety. To Supplicate, and not earneſtly to Pray, is to propoſe to be <hi>denyed,</hi> hee meanes not to obtaine that leaves off in the very <hi>Prologue:</hi> To Pray, and not to intercede, is to be <hi>afraid</hi> to be heard, to thinke we ſhall be <hi>puniſhed</hi> with a grant: To Supplicate, to Pray, and Intercede, and yet to intend no retribution of thankes, is rather an expoſtulation for a <hi>due,</hi> than a recognition of a <hi>Boone.</hi> That therefore this <hi>Juge Sacrificium</hi> of the Church may a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcend as a well pleaſing Incenſe, it muſt be our care to leave out none of theſe <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtolicall</hi> ingredients, but to make a happy <hi>Compound</hi> of Prayers, Supplications, Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſions, and thankſgivings, and that <hi>[For all men.]</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There is no man ſo bad, but he may chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenge our Prayers, and none ſo good, but he may have need of them. The choyceſt of men are not the abſolute, though the principall Subject of our Devotion. It's ſo with our <hi>Prayers</hi> as with our <hi>Almeſaeedes,</hi> by the one we doe good to all, but eſpecially to the houſhold of Faith, by the other we
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:112111:7"/>are to ſolicite <hi>God</hi> for every Man, though in a peculiar, and more fervent relation for the <hi>chiefe</hi> of men. There be ſome who will have none comprehended within the liſt of their prayers, but ſuch as are ſure of the benefit. Will you have their reaſon? It's farre fetch'd, even from the cloſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of the Almighty, and grounded upon his eternall purpoſe. There is no reaſon, ſay they, to pray for their ſalvation, which God hath never promiſed, or to wiſh them eternall bliſſe, whom he hath aſſured us he will con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demne. By way of anſwer, I muſt confeſſe I ſhould be ready to joyn hands with them could they but ſhow me who theſe were. But where is the <hi>Counſellor</hi> of the <hi>Lord,</hi> that dares ſay, this Man is a veſſell of wrath, that other is the childe of <hi>Beliall,</hi> and of a third that he is infallibly allotted to eternall perdition. Since the reprobation of any is locked up in <hi>Gods</hi> owne boſome, and that he, who is a wilde Olive to day, to morrow may be grafted into a better ſtocke, I ſee no pretence why this Catholique duty of pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for all ſhould not be enlarged to high and low, good or bad. What if they dwell
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:112111:7"/>in darkeneſſe, and the ſhadow of death? What if their religion be Idolatry, and a meere contradiction to piety? The more miſery and infidelity we ſee them plunged in, the more doth Chriſtian affection bind us to pity their eſtate, and ſtudy their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion. Charity, which hopes all things, prayes alſo for all men, and it becomes not us altogether to condemne any man, whoſe repentance is not yet cut off by death. There is a diſtinction, and God that knowes it made it, but we muſt doe our owne work, and let God alone with his.</p>
            <p>Now if any ſhall yet queſtion how the <hi>Almighty</hi> can accept thoſe prayers, which are ſometimes againſt his will, though not with our knowledge: Let him know, ſaith Saint <hi>Auſtin,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Enchir.</note> that a man may with a will that is good, will that, which <hi>God</hi> will not, ſo he ſubmits to <hi>Gods</hi> will, and reſt when it appeares. For the generall <hi>revealed</hi> will of <hi>God,</hi> which is here expreſſed to pray for <hi>all men,</hi> being the rule of our actions, and not that, which remaines <hi>ſecret,</hi> our requeſts for things oppoſite to this <hi>ſecret</hi> will are not the leſſe gratious in his ſight.</p>
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:112111:8"/>
            <p>Wherefore 'tis a <hi>Calumny</hi> to object wee pray to <hi>God</hi> to ſave thoſe men, whom hee determines not to ſave, whereas our pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, abſtracting from the reprobation of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny private perſon, deſire no more than in poſſibility may be, and that alſo not pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remptorily, but meekely proſtrating our wils, and requeſts to his pleaſure, and gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious interpretation. But can we doubt to pray for <hi>all men,</hi> when <hi>Chriſt</hi> himſelfe hath enjoyn'd us by Command, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded us by example? Looke upon him on the Croſſe, and behold, when the whole man was batter'd, and every part beſieg'd with a diſtinct death, when the tongue on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly enjoy'd a ſhort truce, he us'd it not to empty his owne ſorrow, but to begge his <hi>Enemies</hi> pardon. Now if this duty includes ſo large a proſpect, as that it eyes all man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind univerſally, even the <hi>Begger</hi> that lyes by the wall hath an intereſt in our prayers, how ought they to bee multiplyed for <hi>Kings,</hi> by whom we have recourſe to our <hi>Oratories,</hi> theſe Offertories of praiſe, and thankſgiving? For although it be the <hi>Lord,</hi> which originally <hi>dat eſſe, &amp; eſcam,</hi> gives us
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:112111:8"/>our life and living, yet it is the Lords <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nointed,</hi> who orders the diſtribution, and metes out every ones <hi>dimenſum,</hi> his juſt ſhare, and thriving portion.</p>
            <p>It is by <hi>him</hi> that we move in our proper ſphere, and are not juſtled out of it. The poore mans <hi>fragments,</hi> and the rich mans <hi>basketfuls</hi> are preſerv'd by his reſtraining <hi>po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer.</hi> Every crum we put into our mouthes, every drop wherwith we coole our tongues the very ayre wee continually breathe in and out, we enjoy by the wiſe govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the <hi>King.</hi> Were it not for the bind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing force of Soveraignty, who durſt raiſe a damme againſt the Torrent of Corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on? Our meetings would be mutinies, our <hi>Pulpits Cockpits,</hi> authority would loſe its au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, no ſubordination, no ſubjection, the honourable would be level'd with the baſe, the prudent with the childe, all would be amaſs'd, and hudled up in an uniuſt pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, and the Land over-runne with in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flexible generations.</p>
            <p>Before the Deluge we reade of no <hi>Kings,</hi> and therefore we find thoſe times to be the worſt of all times, the inundation of <hi>vice</hi>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:112111:9"/>being a greater plague than that other of the <hi>Flood.</hi> Turne to the <hi>Annals</hi> of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> in the booke of <hi>Judges,</hi> Chap. 17.19.21. and there <hi>Micah's</hi> Idolatry, the defiling of the <hi>Levites</hi> wife after an inſatiable, and bru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſh manner, the bloody deſtruction of <hi>Ja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bes Gilead,</hi> the rape of Virgins by fraud, and violence, theſe, and much more may ſerve as a ſad ſtory, how it is farre better to live under an evill <hi>King</hi> than no <hi>King.</hi> In thoſe dayes miſchiefe did <hi>raigne,</hi> and knew no bounds, all villanies were let looſe, and armed, ſtanding like theeves by the high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way ſide at noone day, becauſe, ſaith the Spirit of <hi>God,</hi> there was no <hi>King</hi> in Iſrael. And therefore though the <hi>Lord</hi> complaines in <hi>Hoſea,</hi> Chap. 8. they had ſet up a <hi>King,</hi> but not by him, yet this doth not inferre that <hi>Majesty</hi> is not <hi>Jure divino, God</hi> being diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſed, not as if the authority of <hi>Kings</hi> was unlawfull, but becauſe their infidelity, and diſtruſt in his loving goodneſſe, the luſt of their owne liberties, their crooked and ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter meanes in purchaſing it, were ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers to him. For of all formes of Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, the <hi>Regall</hi> is the beſt: <hi>Tacitus</hi> ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerves
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:112111:9"/>in the firſt of his <hi>Annals,</hi> how certaine wiſe men diſcourſing of the life of <hi>Auguſtus,</hi> after his death, affirmed rightly that there was no other meanes to appeaſe the diſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders of a <hi>State,</hi> but by reducing it under the <hi>Principality</hi> of one. A glimpſe whereof ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peares through the whole courſe of <hi>nature.</hi> For as <hi>God</hi> is one, who ruleth all, ſo he hath created one chiefeſt <hi>Light,</hi> to be <hi>Maſter</hi> of the day, and the <hi>Moone</hi> at night. You can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not take a turne in ſome Gardens, but you may behold among the little <hi>Bees,</hi> one like a <hi>Monarch</hi> leading the ſwarme, and the reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>due attending. Among the <hi>Cranes</hi> one flies before, and one is <hi>Sentinell</hi> for the whole Company: in brute beaſts, one guides the flocke, and is as it were Herdſ-man to all the reſt. And may it not hence be gathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, that man as far as may be, ſhould like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe be conform'd to <hi>Nature?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>How dare then the <hi>Anabaptiſts</hi> deduce their <hi>Anarchy</hi> from the Law of <hi>God,</hi> that ſo they may <hi>outlaw</hi> the Law of man? Saint <hi>Paul</hi> in the fifth Chapter to the <hi>Galatians,</hi> bids us ſtand faſt in the <hi>Liberty</hi> wherewith <hi>Chriſt</hi>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:112111:10"/>hath made us free, they therefore will ſpurne at humane authority, as if <hi>Christi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anity,</hi> and obedience to the <hi>Magiſtrate,</hi> were incompatible, and in themſelves repugnant. If they would reflect on the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> to the <hi>Corin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thians,</hi> and the 15. the ſame <hi>Apoſtle</hi> would warrant them, that rule, and authority muſt hold till the laſt day of Iudgement, when the Kingdome is delivered up to <hi>God</hi> the Father. If ſickneſſe be here, it is expedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent that here we ſhould have Phyſicke; and if we be ſubject to tranſgreſſe, there muſt be government to ſuppreſſe, and cenſure. But if they bee ſo pure that they cannot quench the <hi>Spirit</hi> of <hi>Grace,</hi> then <hi>Kings</hi> are advanc'd to erect for them <hi>Trophes,</hi> and Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>numents of glory. For if you doe well, you ſhall have praiſe of authority, 1 Epiſt. of Saint <hi>Peter</hi> chap 2.</p>
            <p>Good <hi>God!</hi> what doe theſe men con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> of the <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> and bleſſed <hi>Martyrs?</hi> Did not the <hi>Apostles</hi> yeeld al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legeance to barbarous Infidels? Dare they ſay our <hi>Saviour</hi> did <hi>temporize,</hi> when he paid tribute to <hi>Caeſar?</hi> Or will they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demne
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:112111:10"/>the <hi>Primitive</hi> times of puſillanimity, in that they patiently hugg'd their death, yeelded their limbes to be torne, and rent aſunder by the cruelty of <hi>Tyrants?</hi> The peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of <hi>Iſrael</hi> exhibited obedience to the <hi>Kings</hi> of <hi>Babylon,</hi> of <hi>Egypt,</hi> of <hi>Perſia.</hi> Thoſe three famous <hi>Jewes</hi> in the third of <hi>Daniel,</hi> were ſo truſty to <hi>Nebuchadnezzar,</hi> that he made them univerſall Governors over all his dominions <hi>Julian</hi> was an unbeleeving Emperour, was he not an <hi>Apoſtata,</hi> an op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſor, an Idolater? and yet,
<note place="margin">In <hi>Pſal.</hi> 124.</note> ſaith Saint <hi>Auſtin,</hi> Chriſtian ſouldiers did ſerve that unbeleeving Emperour.</p>
            <p>When they came to the cauſe of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> they would acknowledge no Lord but him which is in heaven; when hee would have them ſacrifice, and worſhip Idols, they preferred <hi>God</hi> before him: But when he ſaid, Goe forth to fight, invade ſuch a Nation, they preſently obeyed, they di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſhed their eternall <hi>Lord</hi> from their temporall, and yet were they ſubject to their temporall <hi>Lord</hi> for his ſake, that was their eternall Lord, and Maſter.</p>
            <p>This ſhould ſchoole unyoked ſtubborn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:112111:11"/>and make each necke plyable unto all manner of Ordinances of man, for the <hi>Lords</hi> ſake, for ſo is the <hi>Will</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.13, 14. For ſeeing all <hi>Kings,</hi> without di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinction, or reſtriction, are Gods Vice-ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents, profound <hi>King James</hi> in his booke of the true Law of free Monarchy, largely proves that ſubmiſſion is to be rendered to them, whether <hi>juſt,</hi> or <hi>unjuſt,</hi> not ſo much as they are <hi>Men,</hi> but as they are the <hi>Depu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> bearing a kind of <hi>Divinity</hi> about them, which makes their perſons and po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer alwaies Sacred, and inviolable. If their iniunctions doe not contradict the greateſt <hi>King,</hi> we are to be nimble by an <hi>active</hi> obedience, in performing what they will; If they cleerely oppugne the Law of God, in caſe we cannot well fly from their fury, we muſt be content by our <hi>paſsive</hi> o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience to yeeld our ſelves to be executed rather than to execute them. <hi>Bonus ſi fue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit qui tibi praeeſt, nutritor tuus eſt; malus fi fuerit, tentator tuus eſt,</hi> is Saint <hi>Auſtins</hi> Doctrine; <hi>Kings,</hi> if they be good, are our <hi>Protectors,</hi> if bad, they are <hi>Gods</hi> Inſtruments to prove our Loyaltie. They are ſtiled the <hi>Rod</hi> of
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:112111:11"/>his fury, a <hi>ſword</hi> to puniſh ſinners. <hi>Aſhur,</hi> the <hi>rod</hi> of my wrath, I will ſend him to a diſſembling Nation, and I will give him a charge againſt the people of my wrath. <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſai.</hi> 10. The Prophet <hi>Jeremy</hi> cals that Ethnick Emperor, <hi>Nebuchadnezzar,</hi> the ſervant of <hi>God Ier.</hi> 34. And Saint <hi>Paul</hi> termes the tyrant <hi>Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ro</hi> in his time, the <hi>Miniſter</hi> of <hi>God, Rom.</hi> 13.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Conci.</hi> 1. <hi>cont. Auxent. de ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſilic. Tradit.</hi>
               </note> This made Saint <hi>Ambroſe</hi> confeſſe that teares were his weapons againſt the armes, and Souldiers of the <hi>Emperour,</hi> that he neither could, nor ought reſiſt. For ſince, as <hi>Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tullian</hi> ſpeakes,
<note place="margin">Ad Scap.</note> they receive from <hi>God</hi> what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever they are, and are only leſſe than <hi>God,</hi> it is not for us vindictively to meddle with them. For who can lay hands on <hi>Gods Anointed,</hi> and be innocent? 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 24. It was ſpoken of <hi>King Saul,</hi> who contrary to all Law, equity, and Religion, had cauſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſly ſlaine the Prieſts of the Lord.</p>
            <p>But though Saint <hi>Ambroſe</hi> in <hi>Apologia Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid</hi> tels us, <hi>Nullis vocatur ad poenam legibus, tutus Imperii Maieſtate,</hi> yet Kings are not to thinke they are exempted from the <hi>directi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> of their Lawes, and from conforming
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:112111:12"/>their actions thereunto. Indeed a <hi>Tyrant</hi> makes his will a Law, becauſe what hee wils he will have to be a Law; but a <hi>good King</hi> makes the Law his will, becauſe he wills that which the Law wils, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore voluntarily impoſeth upon himſelfe a neceſſity of keeping it, that thereby he may ſet a keener edge upon his Subjects to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve it. For the light of <hi>Governours</hi> good example, like the riſing of the <hi>Sunne,</hi> will paſſe into all the Corners of their Domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</p>
            <p>Beſides, the very name <hi>Rex</hi> comming <hi>à Regendo,</hi> from ruling, doth include that with their Regall dignity, there is a mutu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all duty, which they are to diſcharge to their Subiects for their ſervice: As to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend Religion, and the Law of God, to maintaine the Fundamentall Lawes of the Kingdome, as his <hi>Majeſty</hi> declares he doth, and will doe, to provide by all poſſible endeavours for the ſafety and peace of the Common wealth. In which, if they ſhall faile, the moſt High <hi>God,</hi> whoſe eyes are al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes on them, to ſee what they doe, will
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:112111:12"/>to the terrour of their ſoules, ſtretch his arme at laſt to give them the ſorer ſtroke: For to them, who walke not worthy of the rich bleſſings they have received, the greatneſſe of their Prerogatives, and exem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptions here in this life, will be the aug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentation of their plagues, and puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments hereafter in the world to come. Thus I have endeavoured to make my ſpeech like a <hi>Bell,</hi> right and fully rung, to ſtrike on both ſides, clearely ſounding the <hi>Due,</hi> and <hi>duty</hi> of the <hi>Ruler,</hi> no leſſe than of thoſe who are under Rule, and Government: For as I abominate thoſe odious, diſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting relations of <hi>Tyrant,</hi> and <hi>Slave,</hi> (with which, <hi>God</hi> be bleſſed, we are not enthral<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led) ſo I ſhall ever ſtudy to cheriſh the ſprightfull, exhilarating dependances be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt <hi>King</hi> and <hi>Subject.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Againe, in regard the King is the ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guard of the People, reaſon good the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple ſhould yeeld all ſubſidiary helpes that tend to the advancement of the honour, and glory of the King. For when the <hi>Soveraigne</hi> is inſufficient by his owne ſtocke to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vide
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:112111:13"/>for the <hi>Publique</hi> good, or his owne <hi>Dignity,</hi> whereupon the <hi>Publique</hi> depends, it is naturall that ſupply be adminiſtred to him from inferiour members; and it is profitable for the members <hi>freely</hi> to yeeld a fitting ſupport, ſince if the <hi>Head</hi> continue drooping, the members will likewiſe lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh in a conſumption.</p>
            <p>And now let me entreate that none im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe a meaning farre wide from my drift. It was never in my heart, or tongue, any way to infringe the proper rights, liberties, and proprieties of the people: I move on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly for a voluntary, free aide, or aſſiſtance. It were a great diſ-ſervice to the King to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flame his Prerogative to the evacuation of the Subjects <hi>Right;</hi> both muſt be kept en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tire to keepe up the King, and Kingdome. Should <hi>Kings</hi> be without right <hi>Prerogatives,</hi> ſome black mouth'd <hi>Rabſhakehs</hi> will not ſpare to cry out they have nought but the <hi>Name</hi> of <hi>Kings</hi> to commend them. And a people not quickned by their Originall pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledges, and native liberties, will prove <hi>Corpus ſine pectore,</hi> a heartleſſe uſeleſſe <hi>trunke,</hi>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:112111:13"/>portending nothing but ſad events, as the beaſts of old were ſaid to doe, when at their ſacrificing, the <hi>heart</hi> was found to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumed. Such a <hi>People</hi> may fill up a number, they will hardly be accounted conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble members of a Commonwealth, becauſe they have no <hi>pulſe</hi> from any <hi>intrinſecall</hi> prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple of their owne, but like <hi>pawnes</hi> at <hi>Cheſſe</hi> are to be moved, and removed onely by the phanſie of the externall Agent. It is therefore the equity, and prudence of his <hi>gratious Majeſty,</hi> ſincerely to profeſſe that he is as tenderly affected to the <hi>Priviledges,</hi> and rights of his Subjects, as to the <hi>preeminence</hi> of his owne Crowne; well knowing hee cannot be a puiſſant King of a flouriſhing Kingdome, but by being King of a free Nation.</p>
            <p>I know no ſtronger motive to confirme your zeale for the Kings honour, then to remember you how <hi>God</hi> himſelfe is ſo zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous of their honour, that in the 16. of the <hi>Proverbs,</hi> he chargeth not to detract from them, ſo much as in our thoughts. Hee knowes what vexations his chiefe <hi>Stewarts</hi>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:112111:14"/>endure under him, and therefore he would have their anguiſh ſweetned with our duti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, and awfull regard. But moſt of us ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mire the heighth of their exaltation, few there are who ſound the depth of their care. We are taken with the gold, and pretious ſtones in their <hi>Crownes,</hi> we con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider not how they are lined with <hi>thornes,</hi> and that there are <hi>thiſtles</hi> in their pillowes as in their <hi>Enſignes.
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Valer. Max. l.</hi> 7.</note> Antigonus</hi> found it, when he told an old wife that was praiſing unto him his happineſſe in his raigne, ſhewing his <hi>Diademe,</hi> that, if ſhe knew how many evils it was ſtuffed with, ſhe would be loath to take it up, if ſhee found it lying on the ground. <hi>Moſes</hi> was a Governour by <hi>Gods</hi> owne appointment, <hi>Numb.</hi> 11. yet he was ſo tyred out that he prayes to be rid of his life. <hi>Charles</hi> the fifth, after a victorious Raigne changed his <hi>Court</hi> for a <hi>Cloyſter.</hi> It is then the leſſe wonder if in that enigmati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call parable propounded by <hi>Jotham, Judges</hi> 9. where the trees went forth to anoynt a King over them; the <hi>Olive</hi> would not leave his fatneſſe to macerate himſelfe with the cares of a Kingdome, nor the <hi>Figge tree</hi> his
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:112111:14"/>ſweetneſſe, to taſte of the bitter ſweetes of a Kingdome; nor the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ine</hi> his fruitfulneſſe, chearing both <hi>God</hi> and Man, to afflict him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe with the barren cares of a Kingdome. And thus becauſe the <hi>Governors</hi> load is grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter than their honour, that they may be won to a chearefull acceptance, ſupplications are to be made joyntly for the <hi>Supreame,</hi> and for the <hi>ſubordinate,</hi> for <hi>Kings,</hi> and all that be in <hi>Authority.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So great is the care of the <hi>Almighty,</hi> to ſee all things well order'd, that he hath placed a threefold ſubordinate Authority in the World, <hi>Domeſticall</hi> in private Families, <hi>Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall</hi> in the Miniſteriall Keyes, and <hi>Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall</hi> in the <hi>Magistrate.</hi> For one as One can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not poſſibly governe many, though his <hi>Princely</hi> minde be accompliſhed with He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roique Excellencies. And therefore as <hi>God</hi> ſuffereth his <hi>Vice-gerents</hi> to ſhare with him in his higheſt Title, ſo hath <hi>Regall</hi> Authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty communicated part of its <hi>Royalty</hi> to their <hi>Subſtitutes,</hi> that the greatneſſe of their truſt may put them in minde of their charge, which is the conſervation of the Kings ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:112111:15"/>and our peace They move like wheeles, one within the other, the leſſer within the greater, yet they all move in the ſtrength of the King, as the under wheeles in <hi>Ezekiels</hi> Viſion did by the great compaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing wheele, which alone appeared. The <hi>Head</hi> derives influence of ſenſe and motion to all the inferior members, whereby they are ſuſtained, yet doth the eye watch, the eare heare, and every ſenſe is employed for the direction of the hands, and feete. So albeit Originally it is the King, which un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der <hi>God</hi> upholds the people, he being called <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,
<note place="margin">See Wiſd. 6.24. A wiſe King accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, called <hi>ſtabilimentum populi;</hi> the ſupport, ſtay, or ſtaffe of the people.</note> as it were the foundati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on on which his ſubjects reſt, yet he hath his eares, and <hi>Intelligencers</hi> for the ordering of the Common good. As therefore we owe allegeance to <hi>God</hi> through the King, ſo we owe it to the King through his authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed <hi>Officers,</hi> by whoſe preſence, and gui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance it comes to paſſe that every man ſits quietly under his owne roofe, which is the end of our prayers, and the Kings care, that we may lead a <hi>quiet, and a peaceable life.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>They breed but ill blood, who hold <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minion</hi>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:112111:15"/>more for the pompe of the <hi>Governor,</hi> than for the benefit of the governed. The Commonwealth of <hi>Rome</hi> made that a quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rell betwixt them, and the <hi>Senate. Menenius Agrippa</hi> compar'd it in his <hi>Apologue</hi> to the variance, which the members of the body had againſt the ſtomach, they objected that it devoured all, and tooke no paines, but lay idly, and ſluggiſhly in the midſt of the body, while the reſt laboured full ſore; and ſo the eye would not ſee for it, nor the hand worke for it, nor the teeth chew for it, but every member refuſed to doe its of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice. The ſtomach ſoone after wanting meate, and being empty, the eye waxed dimme, the hand weake, the feet feeble, all the body began to languiſh and pine away, inſomuch that at the laſt they were compel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led to afford their mutuall Offices for the ſtrength of the ſtomach, that ſo themſelves might be ſtrengthened. Thus it fares be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene the <hi>King</hi> and the <hi>People,</hi> for ſubje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction is more for the good of the <hi>State,</hi> than for the ſtate of the <hi>King.</hi> Hereupon ſome vvould have <hi>Diadema</hi> compounded of <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, vvhich may in a Greeke conjuncti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:112111:16"/>of words be ſometimes uſed for <hi>For,</hi> and <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, which is the <hi>People.</hi> And not onely prophane Writers, but Saint <hi>Paul,</hi> 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2. makes <hi>Coronam</hi> to ſignify the <hi>People;</hi> A faire remembrance, that as the <hi>Crowne</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſeth the <hi>Kings</hi> head, ſo is <hi>he</hi> ſet in the middeſt of his Subjects to be employed for their welfare; the concord, and tranquil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity of the Commonwealth, being his grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt honour, and felicity.</p>
            <p>The Embleme of the <hi>Netherlands</hi> by ſtamping money with two <hi>earthen pots</hi> ſwimming in the Sea,
<note place="margin">Cambdens E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liz.</note> and wittily inſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bing, <hi>Si collidimur, frangimur,</hi> if we <hi>knocke to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether</hi> we are <hi>broken,</hi> hath a uſefull Morall for theſe times. Should we come to heare the dreadfull, and confuſed noyſe of Warre, the thundring of the <hi>Ord'nances;</hi> If our ploughſhares ſhould be turn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d into ſwords, and our ſithes into ſpeares, the famine of bread, cleaneneſſe of teeth, and dearth of all good things, would make us fill the eares of Heaven with Orizons for <hi>Kings,</hi> and <hi>all that be in Authority,</hi> that we may lead a quiet and peaceable life. But wee are
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:112111:16"/>growne fat with peace, and ſo beginne to loath it, as <hi>Iſrael</hi> did their <hi>Manna;</hi> it's made by moſt the fuell of vice, an occaſion of looſeneſſe, and ſecure idleneſſe, as if wee ſaid within our ſelves as <hi>Babell</hi> did in her proſperity, We ſhall never be moved, there ſhall be no <hi>leading into captivity,</hi> nor com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaining in our ſtreetes. A great impedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of our quiet, and peaceable life are homebred, and <hi>domeſticall</hi> foes. The firſt are <hi>Papiſts, falſe-hearted, forraine-hearted Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts</hi> I meane, who have a tongue for the <hi>King,</hi> and a heart for his enemies, <hi>Jacobs</hi> voyce, <hi>Eſau's</hi> hands, who will be ready at every turne to open the doore, and let the thiefe in, and like ſly Foxes will ſhew the way for the wilde Boare to deſtroy. How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever they pretend a deteſtation of thoſe more then inhumane cruelties, which their <hi>Pſeudocatholique</hi> fraternity inflict upon blee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding <hi>Ireland,</hi> yet ſhould they get the maſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry here, which I truſt Gods goodneſſe will ever prevent, we muſt expect no mercy. <hi>Geball, Ammon,</hi> &amp; <hi>Amalek, Spaine,</hi> the <hi>Pope,</hi> &amp; the <hi>Eagle</hi> would flye upon us, and combine all their forces to devoure us. For as <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>homet</hi>
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:112111:17"/>in his Alchoran promiſeth the high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt ſeate in heaven to him that kills moſt <hi>Chriſtians,</hi>
               <note place="margin">See <hi>Phil. Morn. l. de ver. Relig. Chr. c.</hi> 33. <hi>p.</hi> 608.</note> ſo the <hi>Pope,</hi> and <hi>Jeſuites</hi> make it a matter meritorious to kill <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retiques, as they pleaſe deſpightfully to terme us, yea the more of us they murther, the more glorious reward they ſhall have in heaven. Yet let us pray to <hi>God</hi> to convert them; as for thoſe which will not be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted, let us beſeech the <hi>All-wiſe God</hi> to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue it in the heart of his <hi>Majeſty,</hi> and the <hi>Parliament,</hi> whom it concernes, to curbe, and keepe them under, not to let them have the remes too much at liberty, leſt they take head, and like a pampered <hi>Palfry</hi> throw their Rider, and bring a ruine to their <hi>King</hi> and <hi>Country</hi> in the end.</p>
            <p>The ſecond <hi>Domeſtique</hi> foes to our quiet, and peaceable life, may be new fangled <hi>Sectaries,</hi> who raſhly condemne whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver their private ſpirits doth diſallow, and eſteeme all diſordered, that hath not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>currence with their particular Tenets. This makes them without warrant to obtrude bold <hi>Pamphlets,</hi> caſting therein the frame of
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:112111:17"/>
               <hi>Religion</hi> in the mould of their owne pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate fancies, as if they would <hi>preſcribe</hi> to <hi>Higher powers,</hi> what they ſhould enact. Saint <hi>Austin</hi> ſpeakes ſharpely againſt ſuch kinde of <hi>Polypragmaticks,</hi> ſtiling them men ſwoln with pride, mad with headineſſe, treache<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous in ſpreading calumnies, turbulent in ſowing ſeditions, who leſt they ſhould be diſcerned to want the light of truth, <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>m<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bram rigidae ſeveritatis obtendunt,</hi> doe caſt forth a glimmering ſhow of demure auſterity. They are the true tranſlated words of that <hi>Father</hi> in his third booke, and firſt chap. <hi>Cont. Parmen.</hi> Saint <hi>Bernard</hi> alſo complaines paſſionately againſt contentions children of the Church: <hi>Pax à Paganis,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Serm.</hi> 33 <hi>ad Paſtor. in Syn. et</hi> 33 <hi>in Cant.</hi>
                  </note> pax ab haere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticis, ſed non profecto à Filiis; Pagans,</hi> ſaith he, fight not, <hi>Heretiques</hi> write not, her children doe both, and rip out <hi>Maternall</hi> trophes by tongue, and pen, maintaining their quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rell <hi>non Ratione, ſed Pertinacia,</hi> not by waight of reaſon, but obſtinate dint of will,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ierom. in c.</hi> 1. <hi>ad Rom.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>bi non Veritas quaeritur, ſed Adverſarius fatigatur,</hi> whoſe ayme is the foyle, and tyring of the Adverſary, never the ſearch of the Truth. For it is the practice of Contention to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:112111:18"/>thoſe errors, which a right Iudgement diſproves,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>In c.</hi> ad <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phoſ.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Nè cedere videatur,</hi> ſaith Saint <hi>Ambroſe,</hi> leſt together with the Tenet, the diſputer might ſeeme to fall. Thus while they debate, thus while they teare, thus while they rend the Church, they give a ſignall to them without, and encourage <hi>Aliens</hi> to joyne blaſphemy with their diſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p>Where is now that ſolemne uſe of una<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimous agreement?
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Apobg. c.</hi> 39.</note> In <hi>Tertullians</hi> dayes there was ſuch unity among <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> that it was <hi>ad ſtuporem Gentium,</hi> to the amazement of the Heathen, See, ſay they, how the <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians</hi> love each other, and are ready to dye one for another! The time was, when one houſe, one boord, yea one ſoule could ſuffice three thouſands, <hi>Act</hi> 4.32. but now, (alas!) we are ſo eſtranged from ſuch good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, that wee dwell aſunder under one private roofe, and they who ſhould be <hi>one fleſh,</hi> nouriſh a faction like <hi>two Nations.</hi> It is that which Saint <hi>Paul</hi> blames among the <hi>Corinthians,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.</note> we heare there is among you envying, and ſtrife, and diviſions, and ſo
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:112111:18"/>he concludes them <hi>carnall.</hi> For ſuch <hi>Schiſmes</hi> are not of the <hi>Spirit,</hi> but workes of <hi>Satan,</hi> and therefore he is properly called in our Engliſh tongue the <hi>Divell,</hi> from <hi>Divello,</hi> which ſignifies to unjoyne, and put aſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der; for he is alwayes labouring to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolve that which <hi>God</hi> hath joyned. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to prevent the ſnare of jarres, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with we may be entangled through admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of mens perſons, and writings, Saint <hi>Auſtins</hi> reſolution in his nineteenth Epiſtle to Saint <hi>Jerome</hi> is to bee embraced. <hi>Alios ita lego,</hi> I ſo read other mens workes, that notwithſtanding their ſanctity, and learning, I am not of their minde, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe the truth of their opinions may appeare <hi>vel Probabili ratione, vel per Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res Canonicos,</hi> either by probable reaſon, or by Canonicall Scripture. For the mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of <hi>Chriſts</hi> holy Church ſhould be ſo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpired with one right faith, as in the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dell of the body, all parts are informed with one ſoule. For ſuch as the <hi>ſoule</hi> is to many members, ſuch is <hi>faith</hi> to many ſoules; If every member had a diſtinct <hi>ſoule,</hi> where were the body? If every ſoule had a diſtinct
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:112111:19"/>forme of <hi>faith,</hi> where were the Church?</p>
            <p>And here give me leave to diſcharge my whole conſcience touching the <hi>repreſenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons</hi> of <hi>ſacred</hi> ſtories, and ſome undoubted Saints, as yet remaining in <hi>Cathedrals,</hi> and <hi>Chappels,</hi> that ſo I may endeavour to remove ſome ſcandall, that hath, or may be taken. My proteſtation is hearty, and ſincere, that I abhorre <hi>adoration</hi> of <hi>Images,</hi> as well <hi>relative<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,</hi> as <hi>abſolutely.</hi> No worſhip is to be given to them, directly in themſelves, nor oblique<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly by reflecting on the <hi>prototypes,</hi> which they repreſent. Where they are yet remaining, they are to be uſed onely as <hi>Ornaments,</hi> or <hi>Hiſtoricall Commemoratives. Gregory</hi> the great, who well might be called the laſt of the beſt, and the firſt of the worſt <hi>Popes,</hi> firſt called Images <hi>Lay-mens Bookes;</hi> the <hi>Popes</hi> ſucceeding made an impious uſe thereof, by teaching they were the onely fit bookes for the Laity to pore on, depriving them of the waters of life, and prohibiting them to reade the Scriptures, contrary to the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe letter of the Scripture. It were ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what tolerable had they interpreted, thoſe
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:112111:19"/>words did onely meane that ignorant men by asking what is ſignifyed by thoſe <hi>Repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentments,</hi> which they ſee pictured before their eyes, and by pondering a right anſwer to their queſtion, might ſo be inſtructed as it were out of a booke, that the piety of ſuch holy perſons, and ſacred acts, which are expreſſed by thoſe viſible objects, ought to be imitated in their lives, and deaths. But ſuch a fober conſtruction hits not the ſcope of their meaning, for they inſtruct the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple downe-right to Idolize them; <hi>Bellarmine</hi> the <hi>Atlas</hi> of their predominant <hi>Hierarchy,</hi> doth not tremble <hi>terminis terminantibus,</hi> in expreſſe termes to averre that the Images of <hi>Chriſt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>De Imagin. Sancto. l.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 21.</note> and the <hi>Saints</hi> are to be worſhipped not onely improperly, but properly, and by themſelves, ſo that they terminate the worſhip preſented to them.</p>
            <p>For my owne part, as I will not contend with ſhadowes, ſo I ſhall never any way ſtrive for ſhadowes, being reſolved to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove no further theſe externall <hi>decorements,</hi> and other <hi>circumſtantials</hi> in <hi>Gods</hi> houſe, then the <hi>Policy</hi> of the Land wherein I live, ſhall
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:112111:20"/>thinke good to ſupport. And this I ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe is to keepe within the compaſſe of lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding <hi>a quiet, and peaceable life, in all godlineſſe, and honeſty,</hi> which is the cloſe of my Text, and the <hi>totall ſumme</hi> of <hi>Chriſtianity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The heathen <hi>Orator</hi> could ſay,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Tull. l.</hi> 1. <hi>de Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fic.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Inter bonos benè agere oportet,</hi> among good, and honeſt men muſt be good, and honeſt dealing; much more they who profeſſe themſelves <hi>Chriſtians</hi> ſhould be thus affected For ſince man is a ſociable Creature, every one owes that naturally to another by which humane ſociety is conſerved: But men cannot live, and converſe, if they may not beleeve, and truſt one another in <hi>godlineſſe,</hi> and <hi>honeſty.</hi> For this ſeeming zeale, this formall honeſty is like the <hi>Trojan</hi> horſe in <hi>Virgil,</hi> which was pretended the gift of <hi>Minerva,</hi> but proved the ruine of <hi>Troy.</hi> So that godlineſſe, and honeſty, faith and good workes muſt not be ſet at oddes, but connexed, and linked in our peaceable life, as the cauſe, and the effect, the Sunne, and the light. For <hi>peace</hi> without <hi>godlineſſe</hi> is a prophane, unhallow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed peace; and <hi>peace</hi> without <hi>honeſty,</hi> is an
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:112111:20"/>adulterate, a counterfeit peace, it turnes the grace of <hi>God</hi> into wantonnes. <hi>In godlineſſe;</hi> otherwiſe our peaceable life is no better then conſenting in a faction, in a combina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; for there's <hi>Concors Odium,</hi> unity in ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred, when men make a league againſt a common good. <hi>Jn honeſty;</hi> that you doe not by holy pretenſes ſwallow widowes houſes, and by colour of diſtributing to pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous uſes ſcrape together what is not your owne; build an <hi>Hoſpitall</hi> for a few, and pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loyne from many; Such a liberality being no better then bountifull cruelty. But our lives muſt be lead in <hi>all godlineſſe, and honeſty,</hi> ſquaring our drifts by our religion, and not our religion by our drifts, as the Epheſians did, who cry'd up <hi>Diana, Diana,</hi> but gaine was in it; they had learn'd to varniſh their filthy lucre with devotion, and to make their <hi>godlineſſe,</hi> yea their <hi>goddeſſe</hi> the hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maid, the <hi>Stalking horſe</hi> to their owne pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate Intereſt. We are to pray for ſuch a peace as Chriſt gave to his Diſciples, a peace, knit together in all godlineſſe, and hone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty. I will follow my <hi>Apoſtle,</hi> and end as I beganne, exhorting all in their ſupplicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:112111:21"/>prayers, Interceſſions, and thankſgi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vings to magnify the <hi>Almighty,</hi> by the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence of whoſe goodneſſe we have a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nowned <hi>King,</hi> who is an indulgent, &amp; care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Father of the Church, and Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth, a conſtant, <hi>Exemplary Encourager,</hi> and Advancer of <hi>all godlineſſe, and honeſty.</hi> Some <hi>Kings</hi> have beene ſo compos'd that <hi>Jngentes Virtutes, &amp; ingentia vitia,</hi> eminent vices no leſſe then eminent vertues held a joynt concurrence in them, as we ſee the droſſe runnes with the metall; but his gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious <hi>Majeſty</hi> is of ſo refin'd, ſo ſanctified a temper, that envy it ſelfe cannot find the leaſt tracke of a raigning vice in him. Who ſee's not hee is <hi>Rex Mitioris Jngenij?</hi> His cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mency, and moderation Proclaime him a <hi>King</hi> of his <hi>paſſions,</hi> as well as of <hi>Nations.</hi> And therefore, <hi>Continue him O Lord long, long con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue him unto us: Protect him against inbred, and forraine Adverſaries, againſt the Foxe at home, and ravening wolves abroad: Let his enemies beſcattered, and thoſe ſlaine that hate him: Make his ſeed to endure for ever, and his throne as the dayes of heaven: Eſtabliſh ſo firme an unity with the Head, and the whole. Body of the Kingdome,
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:112111:21"/>that there ever be an happy entercourſe of Love and Protection, obedience and ſervice. Let no cunning of Satan, nor any machination of his ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herents be able to withdraw them from leading quiet, and peaceable lives in all godlineſſe, and honesty, through Jeſus Christ our Lord,</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>Amen.</closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
